[Music]
Hey.
Heat. Hey, Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Ask a Budget show.
Today we are in episode
239. So let's see who all is there on
the live stream and then we will get
into the questions. I'm going to take
questions from the comments. Questions
that you've asked in the comments. So
let's see who all is there. I can see
Kalyani Deshmok Krishna Govinda Alfred
Rakunath Baloray Akash Ba British SK
Tushar Kaluri Xmas Yimus Zeus
Geopolitical Dubai from
Indor Nishal Ray Manuk Krishna Oscar
Madison Sunonny Loha Shri Ramchandra
Namaha who else do we have let's see
Sahil Das Gupta Akash Wamshi Khm Nutan
Roshan Chitan Dish
Pandean Prixan Sunonny loyia Utah Tajjis
B Somi Jen Mateo Perez from Texas Rashil
Ju 1813 Disha plays Rogue Gamer Rajumar
rational thinker by Khalik so Anandpai
Rohan Jangid Sahil Das Gupta Vidhi Mar
with a military salute Aayush Solat
Hitender Takur Mustafa Avin Mr. 88ers
prane Paul from Kolkata Akash Ba who
else do we have we have so many other
people anonymous Pam Kumar Singh God was
alive Samart Tripati JJ Hariana
Xenomorph forces Arian Saha Prahar Gupta
Daddy of Diddi's
Dulu Dilip Kgoy Rogue Gamer Prexen
Mahish Rishta Arian Abdul Porkar uh
Anant Pai lost child deadly ninja
Jagdish Mali Amisha Mishra Sonat,
Roshil, Jesal, Ankita, Storyteller, Mr.
88 and so many other people. Okay, I'm
going to end I'm going to stop that now
and let's get into the questions. I've
taken questions that you've asked in the
comments. So, let's take some of let's
let's get going with that. What's
question one? Sort of
says
comment. He's saying that there's no
point asking questions. You never take
the questions. Look, uh, I'm sorry you
feel that way. And I can understand the
frustration when so many people ask
questions, hundreds of questions every
week. I'm going to only take a few,
right? I have a 2hour roughly time
period here, time slot in which I answer
the questions. So I can take maybe 20 30
questions at the most. So how do you
ensure? So first of all, for people who
may be wondering, how do you ask
questions for the Ask a Widget Show? you
ask the questions in the comments in any
video or on the on the community page
and hopefully you use the hashtag
askabjit so that I can search for that
hashtag only and not look for the other
random you know whatever other
commentaries happening in the comment
section so use the hashtag askabjit ask
your question in the in the comments of
any video and I'll be able to find it on
my YouTube dashboard okay and then if
you want me to take your questions if
you want to have a higher chance of me
taking your questions please ask the
best possible questions that will help
everybody that will help the wider
audience. Okay, look I there's no right
question, wrong question. There's no
stupid question. I don't believe in all
of that. But I have answered most of the
easiest questions a long time ago. I
started this uh show askit in what 2021
May June somewhere around that time and
I have answered all the questions you
can imagine. All the simple questions
are have been answered multiple times
and they're available on this channel or
on the Abijah clips channel. All the
individual uh clips of each question
being answered. So if you want if you're
wondering why I'm not taking it up,
maybe I've answered it multiple times.
So look it up. It's available. It's all
it's all there on YouTube. Just uh
search for my name, search for the
hashtag askit and put your question in
there. Most likely you'll find it.
Right? So I've answer if you ask me once
again what is when are we taking back P.
I'm not taking that question. You got to
ask good questions that will help
everybody something new, something
interesting, a new angle or something.
And if you are a regular viewer of this
show, you know what things interest me.
History, geopolitics, science mainly. In
science, it's more physics than other
sciences. In history, it's world
history. In geopolitics is about what's
happening right now. Glo great power
competition and so on. So that's that's
the things you should focus on. So you
know, don't get don't let don't get
discouraged, but please ask the best
possible questions. Right? Let's go to
the next question. True Dollar says,
"How can you possibly be anti-Marxist
when the labor theory of value is the
only empirically tested theory of value
and dialectical materialism is a very
logical lens of analysis? I can
understand criticism of Marxist
revolutions and their attempts of
egalitarianism. Egalitarianism just like
I understand criticism of the vast
majority of capitalist societies. But it
doesn't make sense to throw out such a
sophisticated theory, especially now
with econophysics actively proving the
LTV. I often see people use use religion
or culture as a space scapegoat rather
than evaluating the facts. But I know
you're more logical in your analysis. So
what's the what's the truth? Is Marxist
a ter Marxism a terrible theory? Look,
Marxism Okay, let let me explain. First
of all, let's let's talk about the
theory of value. Then let's talk about
uh dialectical materialism as a lens of
analysis. So what is the Marxist theory
of value? It is see KL Marx is regarded
as as a political scientist. He is
regarded as a philosopher and he's also
regarded as an economist. Okay. So there
is something called Marxist economics
and that's that's a lens through which
one can certainly study uh economics. So
in within Marxist economics there is a
core concept called the Marxist labor
theory of labor theory of value let's
call it that. So this proposes that the
value of any commodity let's say you
have a commodity let's say
potatoes or let's say
bricks or let's say 1 kilo of concrete
or cement whatever the value whatever
the commodity is let's take any
hypothetical commodity it's this says
this theory says that the value of a
commodity is determined by the amount of
socially necessary labor time required
to produce it socially
necessary labor time how much of that is
required to produce a commodity let's
say 1 kilo of one commodity that is the
value of the
commodity okay so the value is
determined by the amount of socially
necessary labor time required to produce
that and this theory is then uh used to
analyze the current global system um
especially capitalism and Marxist
economics arg argues it says that
capitalists that the capitalist system
it is an exploitative system. It
exploits workers by stealing or
appropriating the surplus value created
by the labor of the
workers. Okay, that's the deal. Now what
is this socially necessary labor time?
It is the average amount of labor time
required to produce let's say 1 kilo of
a commodity under normal conditions
considering things like what is the
level of technology and what is the
average uh social productivity of a
worker and so on. So that is socially
necessary labor time. Then there is
something called surplus value that I
just said. So what is surplus value?
Surplus value is the difference between
the value of a commodity produced by a
worker and the wages paid to the worker.
So what's the value of the commodity?
It's determined by the social by the
amount of socially necessary labor time
according to this theory Marxist labor
theory of value. Okay. So that according
to this theory is the actual value of
the
commodity. And the surplus value is the
difference between the actual value and
the wages that are paid to the worker.
And let's say the value of a commodity
is X and the worker is paid Y then the Y
amount of Y money then X minus Y is the
surplus and that is stolen by the cap by
the capitalist according to KL Marx and
that is exploitation. So according to
Marxism, Marxist economics, capitalism
inherently exploits workers by paying
them less than the value they create and
this leads to unending profits for the
capitalists and unending exploitation of
the
workers. All right, sounds good. Sounds
good. Now let's let's uh ask a couple of
questions.
H how do you genuinely determine the
value of a
commodity? Is it only going to be
determined by labor time? How much labor
was put into producing 1 kilo of ur of
potatoes? Yeah. How do you determine the
actual
value? Some people like mangoes rather
than potatoes. So, shouldn't they value
mangoes more? Or some people like
radishes or carrots more than potatoes.
Will they not pay be willing to pay more
for those radishes and carrots rather
than
potatoes? So isn't it true that value
actual value is determined by these
subjective preferences and how useful
some a commodity is rather than the
labor time. Let's say I go and dig 1
kilo of uranium and somebody else is
create is saying using the same time to
to produce 1 kilo of potatoes. Which one
is more valuable? Are potatoes and
uranium the same
thing? Clearly not. So that's number
one. Okay. Value is subjective. It's
determined by subjective preferences of
people and the utility of what's being
produced, not by simply uh the amount of
socially useful labor time. Right? And
then how do you put a number or a value
on nonproduced
goods? How do you put a value on that?
One hour of of music. Let's say I I do a
concert, one hour of I play the guitar
for 1 hour. What's the value of that? I
mean, yeah, sure, I put one hour into
that, but there are artists who will
charge a million dollars for one hour
and people will be willing to pay that.
How does Marxism explain that? And how
do you uh put a put put put how do you
assign a value to
services? How do you assign a value to
intangible assets and all that? So there
are issues with Marxism. It's not that
good of a lens. Okay. Society is much
more complex than that. Now now there's
this other term over here. Then here
here yeah here yeah here yeah here yeah
here yeah here yeah here here a
dialectical materialism. My god what a
staggeringly intellectual term. The
moment you hear terms like these
proletariat and dialectical materialism
and terms like that you you
automatically imagine Marxism is this
super hyper intellectual theory only can
which can only be understood understood
by people of IQ 150
plus right let's break this down
dialectical materialism this is the
philosophical foundation of Marxism
let's break it down in reasonably simple
language so to first of all let me let
me give you a very concise explanation
of dialectical materialism. According to
this philosophical uh underpinning of
Marxism or foundation of Marxism
dialectical materialism according to
this reality the world around us reality
changes through material contradictions
or rather economic contradictions and it
is these contradictions that drive
history forward.
Okay, obviously that has gone above your
head because it will go above anybody's
head. So let's first let's break it down
further. H material see reality changes
through material which is economic
contradictions and these contradictions
drive history forward. That is the basis
of Marxism dialectic materialism. Now
what is materialism? H
material
contradictions. So that is something to
do with materialism right? What is
materialism? So materialism says that it
is the physical world around us that is
the foundation of reality. It is the
physical world which is the foundation
of reality not ideas not thoughts only
the physical world is the foundation of
reality. that kind of hearkens back to
the Charvaka philosophy of within which
is a subset of Hinduism, right? It's one
of the philosophical schools of thought
very little philosophy in that. But
yeah, so that's materialism. The
physical world is the foundation of
reality.
So, so the idea that I the the the cons
the idea that ideas create the world
marks disagrees with that and Markx says
that human consciousness and everything
that we experience etc is shaped by
material conditions like the
availability of food availability of
shelter the kind of technology that's
available to you and
work okay so Mark says that these are
the things that shape human
consciousness and your thoughts and
beliefs and your culture and your
religion all that emerge from your
relationship with the material
world. Okay? And there is an element of
truth to it. No doubt about
it. Right? So he says that it is not the
consciousness of humans. It is not ideas
that determines the qual quality of
their life and the experience of their
being. Rather it is u rather their
social conditions that their their
social being.
It is it is the conditions of the world
they inhabit and the circumstances that
they are living in which determines
their consciousness, the quality of
their consciousness. That's what marks.
Okay. So if you were to put it in
economic terms, it means that the
economic structure of society creates an
ideological structure which is which
manifests itself in the in terms of laws
and politics and religion and philosophy
and so on. So Marx inverts everything.
Okay, that's what it says. So there is a
school of thought called so so there's a
school of thought called great man
theory which says that it is not these
average conditions of the world that
shape history. It is a few great men who
shape
history. But Marx is the opposite. He
says that everything is based on the law
of averages and the average conditions
determine the the the overall uh quality
of the of of existence of humans and
everything emerges from your
relationship to the material world. So
that is materialism. Now what is
dialectics? Dialectics is a method of
understanding change through
contradiction. It is borrow borrowed by
from a philosopher called Hegel but it's
twisted. Okay. So dialectic says that
conflict drives change which is not a
very big claim to make but it's about
change understanding change through
contradiction. Okay. So according to
dialectics there is an existing state of
things. Everything is normal. Right?
This is called
thesis. Thesis. For example in the old
world you had something called
feudalism. Federalism means that you had
uh royalty- class aristocracy and then
you had nobles who would hold the land
for the for the
king in exchange for military service
and they would make the average average
person the peasants work brutally for
them in exchange nominally for military
protection. That's feudalism. So but
there was a time in the world when
everything when when when Europe in in
Europe there was a time in Europe when
the whole society of Europe was a feudal
society feudalism. So that was the
existing state of things that was the
thesis. Okay. So there is an existing
state of things. It's called thesis.
Then there is an internal
contradiction or opposing force within
this existing state of things. This is
called the antithesis of that thesis.
For example, in the time in the feudal
times, there was the rise of the
merchant
class. This was an opposing force. So
there is thesis, there is antithesis,
and then there is synthesis, the outcome
of conflict, a new stage which is
capitalism, which came out of the
conflict between the feudal feudal
system and the merchant class. The rise
of the merchant class, it gave rise to
capitalism. Okay. So all the money was
then concentrated not in the hands of
the nobility in the in the aristocracy,
the monarchy, but the merchant class.
And cities became the big deal.
Everybody started gravitating to cities.
Okay. So the value was no longer tied in
the land. It was tied in the goods that
were produced by in urban centers and so
on. So that was the outcome of conflict
synthesis and this created capitalism.
Okay. So um there's a key principle in
dialectics that every system contains
the seeds of its own destruction through
internal contradictions. So you put
materialism and and dialectics together
we get dialectic materialism. So
materialism says that economy is the
basis of society. Dialectics says that
change comes through contradictions
within a system. So society according to
dialectical materialism society changes
when material contradictions like
especially class struggles reach a
breaken point. So there was a feudal
system and there was a contradiction
which of the rise of capitalism and it
gave rise to capitalism. In capitalism
we have the bourgeoisi the the people
who own the means of production and we
have the proletariat who actually
produce stuff the workers and then
there's the contradiction between these
two opposing forces and that is the rise
of
socialism. Okay so that sort of thing
and we know that all all systems are
inherently unstable and you need some
kind all that sort of thing. Um
so so all of this so this entire thing
is called dialectical materialism. Okay.
Um so according to Marx in Marxist uh
the Marxist worldview the reality is
material. It's all material reality.
There's nothing spiritual. There's no
spiritual component to reality. There's
no idealism in this. It's all
materialism. History according to
Marxism is a process driven by class
struggle. Change happens because of
dialectics. Contradictions within a
system. And contradictions are
essentially always between classes.
And the classes can be classified very
simply into the oppressors and the
oppressed. And the end goal of socialism
is a classless society, communism via
socialism in which there are no longer
any oppressors and the oppressed have a
revolution and a dictatorship of the
own. The dictatorship of the
proletariat and Marx saw this
dialectical materialism as a scientific
method of history, a scientific method
of inquiry of history. And uh it was not
wishful thinking but it was kind of a
predictive framework. And dialectical
materialism is what the Chinese adopted
during the era of Maoatong. And they
shot people who who were teaching
quantum mechanics because quantum
mechanics is it goes against dialectical
materialism that sort of thing. Okay. So
all of this is what this gentleman $2 is
saying. Labor theory of value. I show
you I showed you the contradictions
within labor theory of value.
Dialectical materialism very logical.
Look at the end of the
day Marxism says that you know the
material world gives rise to everything.
There are no ideas. It's all it's the
material world that creates it's which
which gives rise to history. It is the
average person who is the driving force
of of change. Uh the society is always
divided between into the oppressed and
the oppressed.
That's a very key point.
Okay. And so on. So Markx believe Markx
does not believe in what they call the
the the that school of thought called
the great man
theory. Okay. So according to Mars it is
Marx is class struggle that uh gives
rise to historical change
always and all actions can be explained
through class struggle. So tell me why
did Alexander the Greek try to invade
India via Persia? Where was the class
struggle in
that? What operation did he face? H why
did Julius Caesar uh conquer Gaul which
is France and then Hispania and then
eventually England the British Isles.
What class struggle was there? Who was
being oppressed? He was the oppressor,
wasn't he? And so what explains that
that historical
shift? You simply can't explain history
through the Marxist lens which seems to
which claims to be a predictive
framework of historical change. Okay.
Um so
Marxism is actually is essentially it it
is um an ideology that you use to
destroy societies.
What you do is look in every society
there's going to be there's going to be
uh a division of labor. Any functioning
society is divided according to division
of labor. Logical. Any company, any
corporation, any government, any
military structure, any structure that
functions properly is a has classes. It
has a structure that a command and
control structure and whatn not whatever
you want to call it. It is divided into
various organs. Now let's destroy the
society. If you want to destroy the
society, all you to say to the average
person is that you are oppressed and
that one person is the oppressor and
then you incite them against
uh you know depending on the nature of
the society it may be easier to incite
or or harder to incite. If you have a
very poor education system, if you don't
don't have any grounding in your your
culture, the society become the pe
average person becomes very easy to
incite and and you know that sort of
thing. So Marxism is
essentially what the average mediocre
person will regard as a
very superior
system. Okay, that's what it is. If you
genuinely are intelligent, you will
understand the internal contradictions
within Marxism. But if you are super
average, if you have an if you have an
IQ of 80 or 90, you will believe that
Marxism is the most intellectual and
greatest theory ever built. And
unfortunately the average person in the
world has that sort of IQ 80 90 100
whatever it is in India what it is what
is it I'm not sure what it is but yeah
so it's very easy to to sway
people by giving all these wonderful
theories dialectical materialism the
tatorship of the proletariat the evil
bourgeois oppressor versus the
oppressed and so on. Okay. So it it
looks like a super intellectual
brilliant way of analyzing society and a
very logical lens of analysis and this
the only empirically tested theory for
everything and so on. Eh come on which
is not quite the case. But you need to
have the ability to think deeply and the
ability of of abstract thought, deep
abstract thought to be able to
deconstruct this and to show that it's
all BS.
Right? All right. There we have it. I
don't know why I del I delved deep into
I don't know what is it. Socialism is
it? Sorry, sociology, economics,
whatever. It's a political science. It's
kind of at the inter intersection of all
this.
All right. Rhdrajit Sarcar says, "Why do
people like personalities who conquered
vast amounts of land, won multiple wars,
expanded their empires, borders, people
don't give a lot of importance to those
personalities who don't who did not do
such things? Is it because of the
violent nature of
humans? We humans are an inherently
violent species. We know that. And we
tend to uh regard uh people who do these
wonderful these gigantic things as great
people. It's called great man
theory that it is the actions of a few
great
men. Great as in great capacity for
violence and stuff. Those are great men
in in this theory. Excuse me. And
according to the theory, it is the
actions of a few great men who shape
history.
So if you look at history, history is
what? A series of wars and conquests,
territorial expansions, the rise and
fall of empires. It's all violence. It's
all warfare. All geopolitical change,
all historical change occurs through
some form of warfare, right? And in
warfare you have these people, these
violent people, people who are uh
skilled in the use of
violence. Not just skilled in the you
know in like physically strong and all
that but skilled in the apply
application the the strategizing the
planning of military campaigns and
applying military violence in in
specific ways. Military violence is
nothing but the focused applic focused u
uh application of energy. It's a focused
expenditure of energy because whether it
is muscle power, whether it is human
beings wielding swords and spears,
whether it is guns, whether it is bows
and arrows, essentially this is all
expenditure of energy. Whether it's uh
you know chemical energy through the
through the through ATP in our bodies
whether it is horse energy horses have
to eat something they eat grass once
again it's chemical energy or whether it
is explosives which is again stored
chemical chemical energy missiles it's
all application of energy so um all
change historically large scale changes
has happened through this and that's why
we tend to regard the people who do
these things who who change the the
shape and state of the world from its
equilibrium position and people who
succeed in doing this we regard them as
great. It's just the way it is. Yeah, it
it is to some extent because we are an
inherently violent species. Some
cultures, some civilizations have
prioritized uh nonviolence as as as the
highest ideal and so on. But most look
if you if you are a pragmatic person
you'll realize that even a society that
uh regards nonviolence as the as the as
the best way of living even that society
has to be prepared for violence because
you know if you are too too nonviolent
others can take advantage of you. It's
just the way it is. So yes we are we are
an inherently violent species and that's
why was one of the reasons why we regard
people like Julius Caesar, Alexander the
Greek and so on as great people.
Isabella says, "Do you think Marxist
ideology is encroaching into India,
especially through movies, education,
influences to dismantle the family
system uh values, etc. like it's been
happening in the west for the past
century. Look, it's not Marxism as such
that that ideology that's encroaching in
India. You don't see people waving flags
with the face of KL Marx. You don't see
people waving communist flags in India.
No, it's it's more subtle than that.
People don't even realize that it is
Marxist
uh the Marxist approach at what at work.
See, Marxism is you can academics have
been lying to you. Academics portray
Marxism as a theory of economics as a as
a theory in political science even as a
philosophical
theory. They portray Marxism as these
things. I'll tell you what Marxism
actually is. Marxism is a socopolitical
toolkit. A toolkit is a box that you
open and there are multiple tools in
there, tools. Marxism is a socopolitical
toolkit. And the objective of Marxism is
to enable a very small number of people
who genuinely understand
Marxism to obtain and retain political
power through any means necessary.
That's the toolkit. The any means
necessary is part of the toolkit.
And the simplest tool and the most
effective tool Marxism has is to
classify any
society
arbitrarily as a society that has
oppressors and oppressed. So all you
have to do is to take a big subsection
of society hopefully in you know in a in
a nation that's rather poor and has a
and has a garbage-like education system.
It's very easy to to make to convince
people to believe this that you are you
have been oppressed for 10,000 years and
these people are your oppressors. Go
destroy them and then you start all
kinds of you know uh create all kinds of
fissures and fragment fragmentation
within society and you divide society
further and further and
further. That's Marxism. Okay. So that
is Marxism at work and you can use other
religions in that. You can use any
movement. You can co-opt it into your
agenda. In in the west, Marxist
academics, they co-opted feminism into
their agenda. They hijacked feminism.
Feminism came from a good
place. There was a need for feminism in
western society because of the way women
were
oppressed
historically. But then it it would no
longer end with women becoming equal.
Now women had to become more equal. And
today you have a situ situation in the
United States in the western world where
men are
emasculated. Okay. It's it will end with
women becoming men and men becoming
women essentially and and so on. So
Marxism Yeah. So it's all about dividing
a country and that we have we are seeing
it in India. It started long ago with
the Arian invasion myth. The Arian
invasion theory and the idea that you
know India is so the Arian invasion
theory says that Sanskrit and Hinduism
are foreign to India. They were brought
in by by arin invaders, oppressors who
have been oppressing the natives for
5,000 years. So right away you can break
a society in
half and then let people fight on the
basis. So then so then what you can say
is that Hinduism is evil. Sanskrit is a
foreign language and you have to throw
throw this
off and any north Indian language is a
language descended from Sanskrit. So
it's a language of oppressors. So you
make people fight among each other. You
start linguistic fights, you start
territorial fights, you start race wars
with we are just one race and so on.
This is Marxism at work. Okay. Um and
then you divide people on the basis of
uh religion. Then you take one religion
and break into 75 religions. Hinduism
then becomes then you take Sikhism and
and Buddhism and Janism out of Hinduism
and then you make them fight if
possible. Then you take whatever is left
from Hindu of Hinduism and then you try
to divide it
further and then you start playing
majority minority politics oppressor and
oppressed politics everywhere but you
give it different shapes and forms and
different names and then you put this
ideological framing in your education
system and that's what we have been
laboring under for the past 75 years no
actually more than 100 years that's how
you destroy a society and we are a great
we are a great case study India and our
political system knows I don't know how
many of the people even understand this
and those who understand this this are
doing nothing. So there you have it. So
that's the situation. That's how Marxism
is being used in India against India's
culture, civilization, society, all of
that. All
right. Okay. Lots of questions about
Miss. Okay. Praneal and Ramalakshmi.
First of all, thank you Ramalmi once
again for all the incredible work you're
doing. I don't know what I would do
without you. help you give us give
everybody
um the luxury of finding each question
individually. So Ram Lakshmi thank you
so much for your help. I really
appreciate that. Now the question is the
questions these questions are about
Trump. So Prane Paul says with Trump's
new 90-day tariff pose for all countries
except China is this not a glaring
admission of economic incoherence? Why
single out China so aggressively when
American consumers from tech to even
toilet paper are deeply dependent on
Chinese supply
chains? Is this a strategic trade car
craft or short-term political theater at
the cost of global economic stability?
What's really going on with Trump's
tariff drama? After all the dramatic
escalation with 125 or 145% tariffs on
China, Trump is suddenly pausing tariffs
for 90 days on over 75 countries and
lowering those with just 10% the
baseline. Is this the art of the deal in
action a strategic retreat or a sign of
deep state pressure? Was China always
the primary target or and now the real
game in is global trade reset
negotiations under US terms? What does a
signal about America's real leverage or
desperation in today's global trade
arena? Trump uh Ram LMI says Trump
announced tariffs and markets fell by a
lot and then pose it on notice. Don't
you think this is um really market
manipulation in its finest? There was a
tweet about Trump posing tariffs way
before it was announced. Okay, a lot's
happening. A lot lot lot lot is
happening clearly.
So, okay, first of all, um 90-day tariff
pause. Why did he pause the tariffs?
Right? So, right now, I I believe uh the
the
tariff uh percentage on China is 145%.
And this is an application of maximum
economic pressure. This is bordering on
outright economic warfare. Okay? And
there's a number of reasons what number
of aims for this. Um so first you apply
tariffs on everybody. You you announce
reciprocal tariffs on everybody. You and
you put out a list of what nation is
what tariff you're applying on what
nation what percentage right and China
gets a huge tariff. I mean what tariff
rate 125%. Initially it was 125%.
Okay. So what happens then? That's what
was done initially. tariffs were applied
on all nations except for Russia because
Russia is already sanctioned. So there's
no point. Now what most nations did is
they reached out to the US that hey uh
there's no need for this. Let's sit
down, let's talk, let us understand your
viewpoint, let you understand my
viewpoint. Let's try and find a
reasonable solution that is good for
both sides. There's no need to fight. So
most nations had that response to the
US. I'm sure our response India was the
same, right? How did China respond to
the tariffs? They applied 84% tariffs
back of the US. Then Trump says, White
House says that China has been
disrespectful to us. Other nations, they
said we want to negotiate, we want, we
want to have talks and we want to find a
proper solution. So to all those nations
we are pausing the tariffs for 90 days 3
months so that we have time to talk it
out and and find a solution individually
bilaterally with each nation 90 days to
do that. So only the 10% baseline tariff
will remain on all nations but no extra
tariffs for anybody else but on China
because you guys fought back and put 84%
on us now instead of 125% it's going to
be 145%.
And then China has hit back once again
and so on. So
essentially this was
about isolating and pressuring China.
The real target was always
China. And you could say uh that this is
economic incoherence or whatever. But I
would say maybe it's a planned strategy.
Okay. And yeah, you could say that
perhaps uh there was big push back in
the US because when you put tariffs on
all nations, uh whatever you're
importing from across the world becomes
shockingly expensive and that can go
give rise to inflation and it can
destroy American companies who depend on
these imports and so on.
So then you what you do if if that you
get the reaction from your domestic
domestic voter base then you pause the
tariffs for all countries except China.
So you can look at it from different
perspectives for sure right is this
market manipulation I think you know if
the American voter perceives this as
market manipulation Trump is Trump is in
big trouble so I don't think it is that
I don't think it's about manipulating
markets for personal gain. It's not that
it's about China. It's a it's it's a
geopolitical move. It's a move that is
aimed
specifically at China. Is this
desperation? Look, there is obviously an
element of leverage. You know, the
ability to impose such incredibly
disruptive
tariffs. It demonstrates the
incredibly
huge weight, let's say, of the US
economy. It demonstrates the US
economy's capacity to influence global
trade flows and and forcing responses
across the world, forcing negotiations
across the world. Okay. And the fact
that the Americans are are have decided
to pause this for 90 days, that itself
is an exercise in leverage. We are
giving you temporary relief contingent
on explicit or implicit future
cooperation. Okay. Is there some
desperation?
Um maybe to some extent there is
desperation. This this essentially this
nuclear option that they have chosen
against China. It could suggest that
prior strategies that they employed
against China less aggressive strategies
have now been deemed as insufficient.
Okay. And obviously the the the fact
that they've paused the tariffs on most
countries that shows that even for the
US there are huge economic costs and
political costs and this entire u what
you could call a maximalist approach
against the whole world is unsustainable
politically, economically etc. Okay,
because this could lead to for the US to
a tremendous amount of self- sustained
economic damage. So uh yeah, the pause
makes sense. the pose that they've used
it definitely makes sense. Now uh PR
talks about the art of the deal. Is this
the art of the deal at work? So the art
of the deal is a book by Trump. It's an
interesting book to read. I would
suggest you read it. You know it's it's
more about negotiation than his style of
negotiating his style of dealing with
people and so on. So that's a framework
that Trump uses the art of the deal
framework. So one of the tactics in this
framework is you create an extreme
opening position which is this universal
set of or set of reciprocal tariffs. You
create an extreme opening position and
then you offer concessions the
pause you offer these concessions so
that you can frame your position
favorably to frame your negotiations
favorably. So you're maintaining maximum
pressure on the real target which is
which is China and then you are giving a
pause to everybody else. So this is
called coercion. You're applying pain
while you're also suggesting a path for
the to give them relief on my terms.
That sort of thing. That's the art of
the deal. That's the framework. Yeah,
for sure. Now
um yeah, the US is dependent on China on
so many things. Look, if you have a
fortress, if you if you have a fortress
and that fortress is dependent on on
goods coming from enemies, then that
that fortress is in deep trouble. So,
you know, doesn't make a lot of lot of
pressure to doesn't make a lot of sense
to keep importing stuff from China from
the US
perspective. So,
uh why China? Okay,
why why isolate China and why pressurize
China? There there are justifications
for this. Look, first of all, there is a
gigantic trade deficit. We in India talk
about the trade deficit with China,
don't we? Uh $90 billion or 120. I don't
know what the number is. But we have a
big trade deficit with China, which
works in China's advantage. Obviously,
it works China's advantage. When it
comes to US China trade, there is a
persistent gigantic trade deficit. I
think it is about $1.2 trillion in
goods. Imagine every year the US is
giving $1.2 trillion to China as a as
the trade deficit. My
god, does it make sense to continue
trade with that country? H doesn't make
sense. That's one. Then uh the Americans
have been accusing China for a very long
time of of intellectual property threat.
Widespread intellectual property threat
threat. I started hearing this for the
first time in the early 2000s, 2003 or
something. Operation Titan Rain, you
know, large scale hacking. They stole
blueprints of of of the F-22 and
whatnot, you know, F-35 which was in its
infancy at the at the time and all kinds
of US military equipment. Uh so
intellectual property theft and the
Chinese have this these
uh um rules for forced technology
transfers. So when an American company
is is uh uh setting up shop in China or
whether if they're having things
manufactured in China, you have forced
technology transfers obviously it will
disadvantage the United States. Okay. Uh
the Chinese give subsidies to their
companies. They make it very easy for
the companies to operate in China unlike
in India. In in India it's the opposite
but whatever. Okay. um and the Chinese
don't give reciprocal access to Chinese
markets to the Americans for American
goods and services. So from that
perspective, it makes sense for the
Americans to cut off all trade with
China. Then there is a national security
perspective. You know there is there
there is this growing perception in the
United States that over reliance on
China for critical goods is is very
dangerous whether it is
pharmacological pharmaceutical
ingredients whether it is rare earth
minerals uh whether it is semiconductors
technological components this is a huge
national security vulnerability you know
if you buy chips from China or you buy
some whatever It may have back doors,
you know, look up what a backdoor is.
And some of this became visible during
the coid9 pandemic and we had supply
chain disruptions and so on. So um the
Americans want to
reshore okay reshore vital industries
back to the US make in America and they
want to reduce their dependency on their
rival for essential materials and
sensitive critical
technologies because like I said a
fortress that is supplied by its enemy
it holds the seeds for its own surrender
in the future and then there is
geopolitics okay because China is the
only large scale challenger messenger to
the US and uh it controls uh it China
seeks to reshape international norms. It
seeks to assert its dominance in places
like the Indo-Pacific region. It wants
to uh become a technological superpower
and and leaprog the US in AI in 5G, 6G
and so on. So if you put economic
pressure on the nation, you're going to
constrain the nation's resources and
slow its its its technological progress,
its military
modernization and so on. So you want to
strategically isolate
Beijing and prevent it from forming
coalitions to counter American pressure.
So you offer different terms to
different to to different people. You
squeeze China maximally, but you offer a
90-day pause to everybody else. So
you're going to fragment the opposition
and maximize American leverage in
dealings with China and so on. So you
know that's that's the big picture that
we are looking at. So right now we are
in the beginnings of the of the new cold
war. This is cold war clearly. Okay.
This is war by other means. This is
economic warfare and uh during the cold
war of the 20th century you had economic
warfare. So here we are now. The world
is changing very very
rapidly. Okay. geopolitical dubet says
is the United States using the same
tactics to um deal with China just the
way they handled Japan in 1985
absolutely not very very different
tactics in the case of Japan and the
case of China is completely different
see Japan is a nation that is in under
complete American control it's a nation
under military occupation permanent
military occupation ever since 1945 when
the Japanese surrendered at the end of
of the Second World War. Japan is under
permanent US military occupation. More
than 130 US military bases, permanent
bases on Japanese soil. And those
American soldiers aren't going anywhere.
And every major decision taken by the
Japanese government in the realms of
international relations, foreign policy
or economic policy, any of those major
decisions have to be green lit by the
US.
there's a committee of American generals
who have to give give the green light
after consulting with their bosses back
in Washington not with the Pentagon
Pentagon or wherever. So in 19 in the
1980s there were the Plaza Accords that
tweaked the interest rates and whatever
else in the Bank of Japan and that was
the the the the onset of the great
Japanese downfall the downfall of the
Japanese economy and it it was a
disaster in very slow
motion and its effects are now very
clear. Japan is is now threatening to
become a middle-income nation from a
super high income
nation. Uh so they destroyed the
Japanese economy in a real slow motion.
You could only see small changes over 5
10 years, 5 10 years. But now it's
become very apparent what was done. So
the Americans had complete control of
Japan. In in the 1980s, Japan was the
world's second largest economy and it
was threatening to become even larger in
economy than the US by the 1990s.
Imagine that's how that's what Japan was
back in the day and they completely
destroyed it. Um the Americans don't
have any such control over the Chinese
economy. The Americans don't have
military uh occupation of China. They
don't control the Chinese uh banks. They
don't don't control the Chinese
government. They control absolutely
nothing about China. And that's why they
have launched now allout economic war
against China the past few weeks past
week or so essentially. That's that's
the real uh that's where the real change
happens. Nothing like Japan. It's it's a
completely different story when it comes
to Japan and
China. Dwight Eisenhower says you're the
only one in the entire mainstream media.
Well, I am not mainstream media. If you
regard YouTube as mainstream media,
well, I'm first of all, I don't see
myself as a media person and I
definitely am not mainstream. Mainstream
is those all those TV debates, 8:00
p.m., 9:00 p.m. debates. That's
mainstream media. Uh anyhow, okay. So I
was the only one who was telling
everyone that the Taliban is an American
masal. And now it's crystal clear. I
hope it's clear. I hope it's
sufficiently clear to everyone. I was
saying it like 2 three years ago when it
was not fashionable to to make make such
statements. But those statements have
come true. Yeah, they have been
vindicated. So the Taliban is a US
uh asset so to say. Uh now it's it
appears there are reports in the
mainstream media uh that the CIA
director is going to visit the Bagram
air base and that the Taliban apparently
has handed over the Bram air base to the
Americans and let me point this out my
friends that the Americans have denied
this and even the Taliban has denied
this. Who was it that said? I think it
was
uh it was the iron chancellor Otoon
Bismar who said never believe anything
until it's been officially denied.
Anyhow, so both sides have denied this.
The Americans have denied it. The
Taliban has also denied this that that
the Americans are taking back control of
Bagram. But hypothetically in a
hypothetical situation where they are
taking over control again. Okay. Okay,
in that hypothetical
situation, what what why would they do
that? Why would the US want to take back
control of the Bram air base? Is it a
pressure tactic against Iran? Is it
aimed at China? Does it have something
to do with Pakistan? And how should
India react to this? All right. So,
finally, I can break out the map. Okay,
we have gone 51 minutes without seeing
the map. So, let's see the map. Where's
the map? Here's the map on the screen
and we're going to look at
Bagram. Here we are. So in case you
don't know, Bagram is in Afghanistan,
Gandhar and it is somewhere near Kabul,
I think north of Kabul some. Oh yeah,
no, here we are with
Bram. So this is the town of Bram. And
if we go to the satellite view, we can
see the air base. Here's the air base.
It has, I think, two
runways. It's a pretty good air base.
Very useful. And let's just check the
length of the air air base just to make
sure we have a good understanding. 3.14
km is essentially you can land any
aircraft no matter how big it is on this
air
brace. And it used to be controlled by
the Soviets during the Soviet occupation
of of Afghanistan.
Um there's this old Soviet air traffic
tower over here. There's a former base
of the Soviet army there. Then the
Americans controlled this base for about
roughly two decades and then they handed
it over to the
Taliban. So now that we understand where
Bagram is in relation to Kabul as you
can see it's about I don't know 50 70 km
or so from Kabul. 45 km from Kabell
roughly give or take. Now let's see its
location in the larger neighborhood. For
example, if I take the distance from
Bram to Shinagar, it's about 500 km. Uh
what about Bram to let's say the border?
Let's say to to Mashad over here 870 km.
Uh the distance from Bram to the Iran
border is about 730 km. And the distance
from Bram to let's
say Tibet
um over here it's about 550 600
kilometers. Okay, we we we we get the
point. And if we're talking about
Russia, Russia is too far away. But uh
Central Asia is not far from
Afghanistan. Just north of Afghanistan,
you have Tajakistan, Usbekistan,
Turkmanistan, all these Central Asian
nations. Um and Central Asia
historically has been uh a Russian a
part of the Russian sphere of influence.
So
now so the question is uh why would the
US want to take control of Bram back
from the Taliban? One factor could be
Iran. Look right now Iran the Americans
consider it as one of their prime
adversaries. Uh they are worried about
the Iranian nuclear program. Um Iran
obviously as we know is u a nation that
is a prime adversary of Israel. There
there have been missile strikes and
counter strikes and air strikes between
the two last year. Um and the Israel is
obviously are very worried about Iranian
capa capabilities. Iran has a strategic
deal with China. Iran is an ally so to
say of Russia. There is military
cooperation between Iran and Russia and
the nuclear capabilities potential
nuclear capabilities are a very
worrisome thing from the western or US
perspective. So uh if you have an air
base in in in Bram, if you have control
of it, if you can fly aircraft from
there, it gives you power projection
capabilities that can definitely
encompass the whole of Iran and also
worry
China. So one target could be Iran.
Okay, you can keep an eye on what's
happening in Iran. If you can fly Awax
or other aircraft um over Afghanistan
which you can uh have them based in
Bagram and you can also strike at Iran
if you need to in that hypothetical
situation from
BRAM that's one so that's a Bram that's
the Iran angle is there a Russia angle
look Russia is far away the Kakistan
Usbakistan Tajakistan Kyrgystan region
Turkmanistan region all of that is part
of the Russian sphere of influence but
Russia is right now occupied with uh in
in in Ukraine very much and it has other
priorities. I don't think Russia is
creating any trouble from the American
perspective in this region. So I would
be skeptical if somebody were to claim
that the Bagram air base if the
Americans are taking it back it's uh
there to counter Russia probably not
Russia. Now let's look eastwards. Uh we
have uh Pakistan we have India obviously
and we have China. China is not very far
about 550 kilometers away. uh that you
know the Shinjang region east
Turkiststan ch or shinjang region of
China now there's a trade war going on
that that's just been unleashed by
President Trump against China and u the
Chinese have long seen Afghanistan as a
as a as a uh strategic area through
which they could have the belt and road
initiative uh infrastructure built the
Chinese are also are investing in in
some industries in Afghanistan whether
it is copper whether it's lithium or
something
various minerals and and so on that
Chinese are interested in that. Um and
the Chinese border is not very far away
less less than 600 km away. So yeah, you
could keep an eye on China and and keep
an eye on everything that's happening in
the Tibet and Shinjang region. If you
could fly an aircraft Awax or whatever
aircraft about 10,000 15 20,000 kilome
20,000 mters above above Afghanistan,
that's another possibility.
Um Pakistan is not that big of a an
issue for the Americans. Um they've
always had this weird relationship with
Pakistan friend as well as enemy at the
same time. Uh but Pakistan is not that
important and I would I would not
imagine they would take Bram just to
keep an eye on
Pakistan. Does it have anything to do
with India? No. India is not really an
enemy of the US. We are kind of quasi
friendly with the US actually in in a
variety of ways. So they don't need to
have Bram to keep an eye on India.
There's a lot of other ways they can do
it if they want to and India is quite
open with the US. So no no such issue.
Um how should India react to this? If
the Americans take back Bram, India
should stay out of it. We stayed out of
it when the Americans occupied
Afghanistan for 20 years and Afghanistan
is is no longer, you know, part of
India. Long time gone. So India should
say it's a foreign country. It's
something that's happening elsewhere and
we we stay out of it. that that should
be India's reaction to this. So if this
is actually happening, I would say it is
most likely a a China related thing more
than Russia or Iran or
Pakistan. Okay. Um let
us one second. What's the next question?
Here it is. Okay. Uh Samana Satish says
one of the conspirators of the Mumbai
terror attacks uh Tahav Rana he has been
extradited back to India or extradited
to India. Is this a diplomatic win and
what significance does it hold? If it's
a diplomatic win, why are we not able to
extradite other terrorists like Dawud
Ibrahim and whoever else? Mr. 88 says
the Havana has been extradited to India.
Can you please tell us about the 2611
attacks? I was too young to understand
the situation back then. Why did that
happen and why was there no retaliation
even though we were already a nuclear
power and also Trey tell us about uh
some journalist okay I don't discuss
people I don't discuss journalist but I
can discuss the other matters okay uh
okay Tahav Rana is a person who was
associated with the attack in some way
um so he's been extradited to India by
the Americans
u is it a diplomatic win and what
significance does it hold I don't see it
as a diplomatic
I see it as a face saver for the
government of India. To be very frank,
the person we want, the terrorist we
want is David Coleman
Headley who uh is the mastermind of the
attack. He knows every single person in
Mumbai in India who was involved in the
conspiracy, who was involved in the
planning, who was involved in the aiding
and abetting of the terrorists and what
not. He knows all those traitors within
India. He knows
exactly you know who was involved. He
also knows the extent of let's say
potential American hypothetical American
involvement if there is any in this. And
he's in a prison in the US. He's the guy
we want. And we have an expedition
treaty with the Americans but the
Americans aren't sending him back to
India. Okay. Daud Gillani. His name is
Daud Gillani. David Coleman Hadley.
Hadley is the name he took to fool
Indians. And he looked I think his
father his his mother was American, a
white lady. So he looked kind of
European and he was able to fool Indians
with his fake uh Christian sounding
name, his kind of whitish skin and his
American
accent. So that's the guy we want.
Tahavur Rana is is a low ranking minion
in the grand grand scheme of things. Um
he's a pawn on the chess board. So it's
not a very big win. I don't know what
good it'll do to us. It's it's a crumb
the Americans have thrown at us. Okay.
It's kind of a face saver. Uh not not
not any great significance. But yeah,
the media will do their runaround and
rigma and mergoround. Uh there going to
be 8:00 p.m. 9:00 p.m. debates for the
next two weeks about this and so on.
Hamjit go we have done a great thing no
not the case the guy we want is is
headed we would also like people like
panoon what's that gur patan singh
panoon who keeps on threatening uh to
destroy Indian airliners etc that sort
of those are the people we should have
extradited to India
anyhow so that's answering satish's
question why are we not able to
extradite other terrorists like dawa I
Daudah Brahim is sitting in Pakistan.
Pakistan is an enemy of India.
Unfortunately, it is um and we don't
have an extradition treaty with Pakistan
and he's one of their key assets. Why
would they extra extra extradite Daw
Ibrahim to us? They won't. Okay. Now, um
what can I say about the 2611 attacks?
Uh happened in Mumbai. I was in Mumbai
at the time. The whole city shut down.
Uh it started in the night sometime. I
don't know 10 11:00 in the night and
there were reports on TV news channels
that there was a gangster shootout in in
Kaba or something. I'm like what
gangster shootout in Kaba? I think it
was about 9:30 or 10:00 or around that
time post 9:00 p.m. I think if I recall
correctly okay some of my what I'm
telling you may not be exactly accurate
because it's been so
long but uh it started with that sort of
news. There's been a shootout in Colaba.
A shootout at what Leopold cafe opposite
the Colaba police station right across
the road like 10 m
away. And so apparently there was a
shootout there. And then the terrorists
went to the Taj hotel which is not far
from the Leopold area. It's uh the
Gateway of India region. And then the
terrorists go inside and take over the
hotel. and another bunch of terrorists
go to the uh Trident Hotel which is at
what Nariman Point I believe which is a
I could put the map on the screen if you
like. Um do we have of course we have
map let's put the map on the screen and
look at
Mumbai. So here we have India. We go
southwards to
Mumbai and we are looking at this
region. So
um okay so we're talking about Colaba
here. Okay this is going to be
interesting. So it starts
um one second.
Let's put the satellites image on the
screen. Okay. The gateway of India is
here. That's my reference point. So you
have Leopold Cafe over here. That's
where the shootout begins. Okay. It's
right opposite a police
station. That's where it begins. And
then the terrorists, they go by a back
road into the Taj Palace Hotel. And then
they take over the hotel.
Excuse me. Then a bunch of
them also go to uh Nariman Point Trident
Hotel and I think it was this hotel if
I'm not mistaken and they take over this
hotel as well and then there's a whole
carnage that happens there and the whole
situation goes on for 2 three days and
the whole city shuts down. Um they they
attack a hospital. I forget the name of
the hospital. And
uh there's a there's a bomb blast in a
taxi somewhere because the terrorists
had traveled by the taxi and they left a
bomb inside that killed the taxi driver
and the taxi and so on. The terrorists
came from Pakistan by boat. Uh they
hijacked an Indian boat, killed the
captain of the boat of that ship, small
boat, ship, whatever fishing fishing
boat. They came all the way to
Mumbai. Um they swam ashore perhaps or
perhaps not. Maybe they were helped by
some locals. I don't know. All the
reconnaissance had been done by David
Headley. So these terrorists knew
exactly where to go. There was a
shootout at the Chhatrapati Shivaji
Maharaj station, railway station. A
whole bunch of people died there and so
on.
They a bunch of them took over the Kabad
house in in Kalaba and there was carnage
there and the Indian administration was
caught completely offg guard completely
unawares the NSG commanders did not come
to Mumbai there was a huge delay for for
some incomprehensible
reason and eventually after two or three
days or whatever it was after disastrous
carnage I don't know the official figure
is 166 people dead including Americans
and foreigners most of them were Indians
of course and eventually uh the
terrorists were all neutralized except
for one who was captured alive because
of a police officer named Tukaram Omblay
great hero who he took the bullets and
died but he ensured that Ajamal Kasab
was captured alive. The terrorists were
all wearing Hindu uh religious uh
items. Their objective was to die so
that it looked like it was a Hindu
terrorist attack but because of Mr.
Tukaraml one terrorist was caught alive
and then it emerged that they were all
Pakistanis the guy was Ajal
Kasab and this thing ends the terrorist
attack ends eventually after two or
three days the prime minister of India
does not open his mouth for the for six
or seven days he doesn't make any
statement and uh we do nothing we should
have flattened Pakistan we should have
flattened Pakistan and apparently the
British intelligence
was was watching this unfold live they
had intelligence they had they had
signals electronic signals coming in
they were watching this live as it
happened so what was the role of the
British intelligence in this as well is
the
question so yeah lots of questions are
still unanswered
uh the perpetrators the masterminds are
in Pakistan uh some of them will or will
may or may not be killed by unknown men
but uh Pakistan has never been made to
pay for this and let's see someday
hopefully if India has
any fortitude of some kind we should uh
ensure that there's justice for the
people who died with the people who died
still haven't received
justice Mr. 88s says Xiinping removed
his army general supposedly the second
strongest man in China, second most
powerful man in the PLA in the people's
liberation army. Is Xiinping feeling the
heat in this tariff wars and maybe
fearing a potential coup in the future?
So
um yeah there is there is this uh uh
Chinese general the second most powerful
general in uh the the Chinese army the
PLA who was uh sacked
apparently and um so I think his name
was Wayong or something. Let's let's
let's look it up. Okay. Uh let's look it
up. Let's go to our friend Google and
let's look for
uh here we have dark mode. Wow. Wow.
That's
pretty
Heong. So this gentleman has been
removed in Xinping's latest
purge.
Um yes. So that's what we hear. China's
President Xiinping removes second top
army leader Kweong's possible downfall
and Xi Shi Xinping's trust deficit and
so on. So, so yeah, it seems to be true
this this news report seems to be true
that the that this Chinese general, the
second most powerful person in the
People's Liberation Army has been
reportedly removed. So if it is true, if
it's confirmed, it seems to be this is a
high level military purge. They call
this sort of thing a purge. And what
could it signify? What could it
represent? It perhaps represents a
consolidation of she's control of Mr.
Xiinping's control over the military.
Right now there are all kinds of
external tensions. There's a massive
trade war that's going on with the US.
The Chinese are pressuring Taiwan like
never before. Military exercises all
across Taiwan. Taiwan is encircled and
so on. So uh maybe Xinping is is
consolidating his control over the
military by removing anybody who could
potentially be a problem problem of any
kind. Okay. So what could this uh
signify? Okay. Okay. Kashi Ping is is
consolidating power. But why did he need
to do this? Was there any internal
disscent in the in in the people liber
people's liberation army or is there a
preparation in China for a new strategic
direction uh requiring absolute loyalty
in the command structure of the army and
was this person perceived as as as a
weak link in this? We're not quite sure.
We don't know. But uh it definitely is
interesting. Now it's interesting to
note that the Chinese are doing this
purge of of their military. But what
about the US? What about NATO? So once
again, let's go to
Google because we should have a balanced
approach uh in looking at things if you
know. So let's look at Google. Okay, our
friend Google and let's look
at
Shana
Chatfield. Shushara Chatfield, USA
Pentagon fires senior officer, Vice
Admiral Shushara Chatfield, a senior
Navy female officer at at NATO uh fired
by Trump administration fired in
expanding national security purge. So
there is the same kind of thing
happening in the in the west as well.
The Chinese are purging their military.
You are seeing NATO being purged of
certain kinds of people as you can see
it's happening there as well. So um and
this this person Shana Chatfield is the
ninth senior officer who has been purged
by the Trump administration. So there is
a purge going on. There's a systematic
removal of various senior military
leaders. Uh why is this happening? Some
of them seem to be associated with
diversity
initiatives. So we seem to be uh
witnessing a fundamental restructuring
of the military command in a way that is
now more aligned with the vision of uh
President Donald
Trump. Okay. So we may be witnessing
fundamental shifts in NATO policy. NATO
policy is driven by the US. Okay. So out
of those nine people who have been
removed, high ranking people, four have
been female officers. So maybe this is
an ideological thing more than a per
performance-based thing. Um or maybe
it's also performance based. We don't
quite know. But we are seeing something
in China. We are seeing something even
bigger in the west in NATO in the US.
Okay. Yeah. Purges on both
sides. Times are changing. Things are
changing. Things are a
foot. Okay. Okay. Pranne Paul says with
India revoking the trans shshipment
facility that allowed Bangladesh
Bangladesh to export to third countries
via Indian land and air routes. Is this
a sharp geopolitical signal to Dhaka and
by extension Beijing following Muhammad
Ununus's uh provocative remarks in
China? Is India drawing a strategic red
line by leveraging logistics as a
geopolitical tool especially? I mean
it's all that stuff. Yeah. Okay. Uh look
uh when you extend a privilege to a
nation, when you extend a facility to a
nation like trans shship shipment, what
is trans shshipment? It means that the
Bangladeshi government, the nation can
use Indian ports and Indian airports to
ship their goods to other third
countries. So we gave that facility to
Bangladesh. Now when did we give this
facility to Bangladesh? when you had a
friendly government in Dhaka pro- India
or at least friendly to India the Shikh
Khazina government so India Bangladesh
ties were very good at the time okay so
that's when we gave this trans
shshipment facility to uh Bangladesh now
we have had a coup in Bangladesh last
year she kasina was ousted she was
removed by the military and a very
strongly anti-India fellow called uh
what's her name Muhammad Yunus is now
the chief adviser to the government or
whatever it is. It's a dictatorship.
It's a military dictatorship and
Muhammadus has been put in place to make
it look like it's a good thing because
he's a Nobel Peace Prize winner. That's
a facade they have
created. Muhammad Inus is a very
strongly anti-India fellow and uh so
look first of all this is a coup that
was done by the US. I made a video about
it nine months before it happened and I
said the US is planning a coup in
Bangladesh and it happened exactly as I
had predicted. So it's a US uh it was a
US regime change operation which means
that Dhaka is now a US wasal. So you
have on both sides of India east and
west you have east Pakistan and west
Pakistan. Bangladesh has been reverted
to its east Pakistan
state. It's an anti-Indian nation now.
And then Muhammad Ninus goes to China
and over there he gives a speech saying
that we will isolate India's far east
northeast it's a landlocked region and
Bangladesh will control the seas and
China should invest in Bangladesh
because India is being squeezed and that
sort of thing that sort of statement he
made and then Muhammad Yunus goes to um
the BIMC conference in in in Bangkok he
meets with Prime Minister Modi and two
days later we do this so
look this is a privilege we had extended
to a friendly country. Now that the
country is no longer friendly, it's it's
adversal to us. We have switched off the
privilege. It's not leverage. It's just
uh our our um it's this
this that's our prerogative to whether
to give somebody this facility or not,
right? Um so we have switched it off.
Obviously, it's a signal that uh if you
are anti-India, you will not get
privileges from India.
Um, is this a signal to Beijing? I think
it's more of a signal to the US because
the Muhammad, you know, regime is not a
pro Beijing regime. It's not a regime
that's supported by by Beijing. It's a
pro- US regime that's supported by the
US. But yeah, indirectly some signal may
also have gone to China, which is
fine. Okay. Okay. Prane Paul says, "If
big tech secretly funded was secretly
funded by DARPA in the US government,
does it mean Silicon Valley has always
been a geopolitical tool rather than a
free market success? How does this
compared to China's statebacked tech
model? What are the global implications?
Okay,
look, some big tech companies were
funded by DARPA.
DARPA is a US government organization
that at any given point in time has
about 150 employees. They have a larger
budget. They have twice the budget of
India's DRDO. They have only 150
employees at any given point in time and
they don't have any office. Who are the
employees of
DARPA? They are typically not really
employees but people who are being
funded by
DARPA and the funds are significant.
So what DARPA does is that it looks
around the country in the US the entire
uh university system especially in the
STEM fields scientific fields it is all
based on research and research and
development research it's
researchbased if you are a professor in
a scientific discipline in the US your
main job is to do research secondary you
teach research is extremely important in
India it's the other way around you
don't do any teaching you don't do any
research you just waste your time on
average. Not not all but not all but on
average. Yeah, that's what you see. So
uh so there's a tremendous amount of
incredibly high quality research,
scientific research being done in
various departments, university
departments all across the country. So
DARPA looks around who's doing what?
Who's doing what? When they find
something interesting, they'll say,
"Hey, here's a bucketload of
cash. Now you are being funded by us.
You take your time.
We're going to ask you how long will it
take to uh see some results? One year,
two years. Just the contract is usually
one or two years. Okay, you want two
years. Okay, here's a gazillion dollars
for 2 years. Go and do your research.
And then whether the research produces
any results or not, that person is
funded for that time. If they get
results, fantastic. If they don't get
results, part of the deal. So that's
what they do. They empower researchers,
DARPA. and they have come up with the
most incredible technologies. Stealth
technology came from DARPA. I think the
internet came from DARPA. All kinds of
in all the
cuttingedge advances in science and
technology in R&D have come from DARPA.
And there are things that have come from
DARPA that we we still don't know about
and they will not be revealed for
another 50 or 100 years. That's what
DARPA does. Similarly, if there are some
tech, there are some tech startups. You
know, somebody is starting a technology
company from their
garage. A college student drops out to
start a company from their garage
because they have a great idea and they
know how to make it work, but they need
funding. DARPA may fund them and they
may end up becoming Microsoft or Google
or something. Okay, that's what DARPA
does. It finds the best people with the
best ideas and with the right skills and
it empowers them. That's how the nation
progresses. So all of Silicon Valley
hasn't been cert secretly funded from DA
by DARPA. But yes, apparently it would
mean that DARPA has midwifed the rise of
many of the great Silicon Valley uh
corporations. Silicon
Valley look any technological
um any any any place that gives the
nation technological breakthroughs is a
geopolitical tool.
it some of the success may be because of
free markets. Some of it may maybe
because the states state had funded it
which is as it should should be uh I
would not say that we should be upset
that the Americans did that. I would be
say that we should be upset we our
government doesn't do these things.
Okay. So yes DARPA has may have been
behind some of the success of some of
the Silicon Valley giants. probably they
were the high likelihood they were but
it doesn't mean that all of Silicon
Valley success is because of DARPA. It's
also an incredibly free place. It's a if
you are in in San Jose, if you are in
Silicon
Valley, you if you have the right ideas
and if you have the right skills, you
will get funded. And it's a place where
all kinds of incredible technology
technological breakthroughs uh are
routinely done. Why don't we have a
place like that with that culture? We
don't have it. Right. Sadly, Bangalore
was supposed to be the Silicon Valley of
India. It's that's not true. Uh it's
it's the cyber capital of India.
I sad to say I'm not trying to be to be
disparaging but you know it's just a
reality. Um so that's that's the deal
with DARPA. How does this compare with
China? The Chinese also have the Chinese
idolized the US. the Chinese have tried
to emulate the US at every possible step
and yeah a lot of the Chinese you know
the way they fund their uh their tech
companies and so on it's it's a it's
very similar to how the US does it so
yeah it's actually quite similar the
Chinese have sought to emulate you know
to study the US understand how they do
things and then try and copy it first
and then try and do it better later so
yeah global implications well forget
about that but you see the global
implications
Okay, Rodri Sarkcar says, "Do you agree
that the US and its satellite states are
now supporting India's claim to the UN
Security Council permanent seat because
they know China will eventually veto the
idea and India won't get the permanent
seat anyway?" Look, look, I don't
understand why we are so hungry for this
permanent seat. Indians chase status,
others chase actual
achievements. What is the point of
getting that godamned UN Security
Council permanent seat? It's a status
symbol. Forget about this. Forget forget
about that thing become so powerful that
that the UN security council becomes
irrelevant. That's what Indians won't
do. We want status status. We want talk
talk talk talk talk
talk and yeah it comes with some
benefits but to hell with those
benefits. Now the US and its satellite
states keep on saying that we support us
India's claim and blah blah blah. You
know it's called lip service. Words
versus actions. Like I keep saying,
words don't mean a thing and they know
that even if they support, the Chinese
won't support. So, so forget about this
goddamn thing. I get so tired of this
entire this talk every day. When are we
getting the UN Security Council
permanency? When are we getting P? When
are we getting a chin? Whatever is in
your control, use that. Work on that.
Whatever be in in someone else's
control, we'll we'll think of that
later,
right? Hersha warrior says, "What do you
think of the Vagaha border ceremony?
Looks like a weird celebration. Do you
think we should stop this nonsense?" We
should stop this nonsense. It's a waste
of time. So, it's like we are treating
Pakistan as an equal. We're giving them
so much space and doing that weird
strutting ceremony and staring at each
other's face and eyes and doing this and
that and all that. It is incredibly
childish, incredibly stupid, incredibly
immature.
Do we really think that we we are equals
with with Pakistan? Pakistan deserve to
be to stand to look eye to eye with us.
Really, why are we going down to that
level? It is stupid. It is silly. It
makes us the world's laughing stock. We
should stop that stupid border
ceremony. Rodrikar says, "Why is Sununzu
so widely popular but Chanaka is not? Is
it because of the positive promotion of
the Chinese culture in world media and
people taking more interest in
it? Um, look, Sununzu, yeah, he's more
famous than Chanaka because the West for
the long longest time was a big fan of
China. Why was the the West a big fan of
China? Because the Chinese had opened up
their market to the West. They had they
agreed to manufacture all of the West's
cheap goods in China. And China was
behaving like a like a nation that has
decided to bow down to the west and and
ally itself with the west. And the west
thought that eventually we'll make China
democratic and we'll completely
transform them. So because China was
cooperating and so on and the west was
was aiding and abating the slow rise of
China. The west thought that okay we
should give China some privileges like
we give to every defeated nation. For
example, a lot of Japanese culture is
popularized the worldwide because of
American promotion like manga and
whatnot. Yeah, all that Japanese anime,
when it comes to anime, when it comes to
South Korea, they have popularized
K-pop, which no one understands a word
of, but K-pop is somehow popular. I just
don't get why. It's because the
Americans have extended their privilege
to the Koreans because they are a vasal
state. They are an occupied state and
occupied states, defeated defeated
nations get some
privileges. Okay. India has refused to
be a defeated nation. I know there are
so many problems problems in India. So
much that's wrong in India. But we are
not a defeated
nation. The west only glorifies defeated
cultures. They destroyed the
Scandinavian culture of the Vikings.
Today they glorify it. They make movies
about it. Thor. Okay. They have
destroyed Samoan culture, defeated it.
They've Christianized them all. Now they
make movies like Moana and so on. What
else? Yeah. Mulan Chinese again right
Japanese
culture there was this movie called
multiverse of misery multiverse of
madness whatever I happened to
unfortunately watch the movie I think
there is this scene in which there's
this big big uh uh meeting and gathering
of all the gods in which Thor and Zeus
come face to face how can Thor and Zeus
come face to face a Greek god and a
Scandinavian god who are the same
god yeah idiotic yeah again they will
glorify Greek gods Because Greek has
been defeated. That culture has been
destroyed. So in that movie, there's
this great meeting of all the
gods. You had gods from obscure
religions but not a single Indian god
because India is not a defeated culture.
So you get it right. Similarly, the west
has promoted
Sunzu and they have completely uh tried
to marginalize
Chanaka. But I would say that Chanaka is
superior.
Okay? Because if you read Sununzu's
little book, The Art of War, you'll find
it's not a book of strategy or
tactics, it's it's not a book that will
aid you to
um to
to construct a a successful military
campaign or construct a successful quasi
military campaign like a World Cup
victory or something. It's not a book of
that. Sunsu's book is a book of strata
gems.
very clever sounding ideas. It's not a
book of strategy. It's a book of
strategems. What's the difference
between a strategy and a
strategm? So, a
strategy is a
comprehensive
overarching plan or a set of plans to
achieve a long-term goal. A long-term
goal. It's a road map on how to achieve
your desired outcome. considering
various factors in various potential
scenarios. That's a strategy. On the
other hand, a strategem which which
Sunzu's book is full of, it is a small
very
specific often clever or deceptive
tactic or scheme used to achieve a
particular small short-term goal often
as part of a bigger strategy. Okay. So
in a strategy you typically will
surprise an opponent or you will
outmaneuver an
opponent. So a strategy is a big picture
plan like deciding how to win the next
world cup. It has so many moving parts,
so many components. A
strategy as opposed to a strategy is a
specific move or tactic within the
plan. Okay. how to defeat this
goalkeeper of this country from this
direction. Okay, so strategy is like
building a bridge and strategy is like
using a clever construction technique to
speed up one component of the build
bridge building process. That's the
difference. Chanaki's book is a book of
strategy. It's a book of straight craft.
It's a book of how to administer a
gigantic subcontinent-sized empire.
Sununzu's book is a book of strategy.
Clever little tactics. Huge difference.
But the west has promoted Sunzu and they
have sought to marginalize
Janaka. There you have
it. Uh geopolitical dub says except the
sun god Surya is there any ancient
rigidic deity
temple except those that are ruin ruins.
What he's asking is do we does anybody
still actively worship any rigid deities
in India? I haven't heard of any temple
dedicated to Lord Indra. That's an
interesting question. Uh let me look up
Rigdic Rigidic deities and let's put
that on
Zcreen. Okay, Google. We do Google. Yes,
Rigic
deities. And of course, it's going to be
Wikipedia. So okay let's look at
Wikipedia. Always remember Wikipedia is
not necessarily a good source of
knowledge. It has it can be very biased
especially when it comes to Indian
culture and history but we're just
looking at it to make things fast. So
Rigidic deities uh deities were
prominence. You have Indra nobody
worships Indra in India today. Uh
Bangkok is called Indra Puri but I'm not
sure whether there's any temple to to
Lord Indra in Bangkok. In India today
nobody worships Indra. Agni. Yeah we
worship Agni. uh Agni is part of our
prayers and homeras
uh Yagnas etc. But there is no temple
dedicated to Agni. But Yagni is Agni is
still somehow present in all all major
you know Hindu rituals indirectly but
nobody nobody directly prays to Agni. S
is the moon. I don't think anybody prays
s anymore. Ashbins okay they pray to
they use the Ashbins uh to to decorate
houses in Lithuania today but not in
India. Vuna uh no one pray prays to Vun
today. No one prays with the maruts.
Mitra nobody ushers vay
savvetra pushan
arhaspati surya we do have sun temples
till
ahro and
pritimata the original god and goddess
of the most primordial Hinduism I
suspect it began with the with the
worship of the skyfather and the earth
mother. I think that was that is the
those are the oldest deities in Hinduism
and today no one even even remembers the
pitu. You will still find small bhortis
of pritu mata in some temples. Okay. But
you will not find any depiction of the
pitru anywhere. No one even remembers
him. But he is the father of all the
gods. Apas adita's vishnu. Well no one
really worships Vishnu anymore.
Brihaspati. No rudra. Okay. Well, rdra
we do we do still worship. We still do
worship rdra. We call him shiva now
mostly. But yeah and yama. Well I don't
think anybody who worships yama. All
people would say is please Yama G stay
away from us as long as
possible. Saraswati. Yeah we still do
pray to Saraswati. The goddess of
wisdom. The river association is almost
gone today forgotten and so on. And
there are minor deities like Ratri,
Aditi and so
on. So yeah, if you twashtar the father
of Vitra, wasn't he? If I'm not
mistaken. And where is Danu? Danu is not
even mentioned here. The great river
goddess, the mother of the
Danavas.
Um, and so on. Mitra
Vun. So if you look at Mitra, he was
once, look, this statue is from
Tajakistan. You may not know but the
ancient border between India and central
Asia was in Tajjakistan even during the
time of Shri Changistan 800 years ago.
And this is a statue of of uh Mitra from
Tajakistan and yeah Mitra is a component
of the Mitra Vun de twin
deities and uh so on post Vic texts etc.
So yeah, you know, we no longer worship
uh Indians no longer worship most of the
rigidic uh gods. Most of these are
forgotten. Imagine how India would have
been, how the subcontinent would have
been during the rigidic time when the
riga was being composed several thousand
years ago. It would have been a
completely different
society. They would have worshiped gods.
Nobody worships today. They would have
spoken Vic Sanskrit, rig Vdic, the
oldest Vic Sanskrit. Their lifestyle
would have been completely different
from what you what you would
imagine. The the food they ate would
have been different. India itself would
have been a whole different place,
completely pastoral place. no uh uh
urban centers, people living um you know
pastoral rural life and so on. The past
like they say is a foreign country and
today's people try to retrop project
today's values and lifestyles upon our
ancestors 5 6 7 8,000 years ago. Let's
be a little more mature and not do that.
Right? You just saw the list a small
representation of the of the gods that
were worshiped during the Vic times the
rigidic time. Nobody most people won't
even know the name of the gods. Today
you think of Indra as some some loser
kind of guy who lives in a palace and
who has absurd dancing in front of him.
The Indra from the
riga was the greatest warrior you can
imagine. He defeated the great serpent
ai a vitra.
You see the depiction of
Thor that's Indra Thor is based on Indra
the god of the thunderbolt and the which
is the vajra and the hammer hammer is
also vajgerra that's
Jupiter that's Zeus and that's
Thor great warrior god the greatest
warrior of all that was Indra and today
they've turned him into the god of rain
was thunder so see you can see how
incredibly ancient our society, our
culture is and how much has changed. Of
all those gods, only RDRA is worshiped
today. But we no longer call him RDRA.
We call him
Shiva and so on.
Yeah. Okay. Um Mr. 88 says, "The dire
wolf is now resurrected after 10,000
years. When are we going to revive
Cambium?" Let me guess. Camarium would
have been some ancient extinct Indian
animal. Let's let's Google it. Yeah. So,
can there be any adverse effects in
reviving extinct animals in our current
ecosystem? Let's go to Google and and
and
and search for these
beasts, the dire wolf and uh
cambeium. So, yeah, we know the dire
wolf is an extinct 10,000 year old wolf
and it's been allegedly resurrected uh
two
puppies. So the deextinction of the
direwolf they're talking about. So they
have uh they
have revived this this species
allegedly. Two uh twin puppies have been
born who look like nice little doggies
but they will grow up to be large
wolves. And the wolf is obviously part
of the dog species but it's the wild
wild version. So the dire wolf was
historically it used to live in I think
North America I believe and it was a
much larger uh in size than the regular
wolf that we are aware of. Even the
regular wolf is kind of bigger than your
your standard issue dog and the direwolf
was larger than most wolves. So what
they did was they okay I have not read
the story but let me tell you what I
think they've done. They would have
recovered a probably a frozen specimen
of a direwolf or some portion some
tissue of a direwolf that would have
been that would have been frozen in the
perafrost. So they get the tissue it's
reasonably undamaged the tissue and you
can extract DNA out of it. Now the
halflife of DNA is about 500 years which
means if you have a sample of DNA in 500
years half of it will be destroyed. The
bonds will break.
So only half of it is left. Then another
500 years half of that half left is gone
and so on. So every 500 years you have
half half half half half. But yeah
10,000 years if it isn't in in perafrost
it may survive reasonably undamaged. So
they were able to they were able to
apparently extract the DNA from that
sample of the direwolf tissue and then
you can inject it using cloning
techniques or whatever into u into a
regular wolf today and that female wolf
will give birth to uh puppies that
apparently are direwolf puppies. So it's
essentially a genetically modified
modern wolf and who has been given uh
direwolf genetics. That's what it is. So
it's not quite the direwolf, but it's
the closest thing we can have today and
it's going to probably have most of the
features that the direwolf used to have.
So that's direwolf. That's how they did
it. Now let's look for
cambeium. Let me guess it must be some
extinct Indian animal. Let's see.
Camarium. Okay. Looks like some form of
I don't know whatever it is. Let me go
to Google. Uh let's quickly look at the
Wikipedia thing. Extinct genus of
placental mammals in the family whatever
whose fossils were found in an open pit
coal mine located in Gujarat India.
Okay. So it's an extinct Indian animal.
When was it alive? The fossils were
dated to the early EU scene 54.5 million
years
ago. Okay. How large was this thing? Uh
it would have weighed about 23 kg and
the smaller one was about 10 kg. So it's
a medium-sized beast. Not very large. 23
kg is not small obviously and so on. Um
so that was cambeium and it was
discovered in Gujarat in western India
and this is kind of what it what at
least looked like and it lived about 54
55 million years let's say 55 million
years okay we have the information we
need now think about it friends
um the halflife of DNA is 500 years
500 54 4 million years is 54 with six
zeros after it. Do you think DNA can
survive that long even in the best
conditions? I would be very skeptical. I
don't think it can. Uh once again, let's
go and ask our friend Google uh oldest
recovered DNA ever. Okay, let's quickly
ask Google what is the oldest DNA that
anybody has recovered. Oldest recovered
DNA. Recovered, discovered, whatever.
Okay. Approximately 2 million years.
Wow, that's amazing. Found in sediments
in Greenland. It was extracted from
frozen soil. Okay. Okay. So, we don't
quite know what DNA it is, but they
discovered some DNA. And the oldest DNA
sequence from physical specimens are
from mammoth mers in Siberia. 1 million
years old. Well, well, well. Okay. So,
up to a million or 2 million, it's
possible years in age. 55 million years.
That's almost dinosaur era. The
dinosaurs were wiped out 66 million
years ago. Not far away from 55. So I
think Cambreum is going to be a gigantic
impossibility. Excuse me. Why? Because
the remains that are available are
fossilized. The bones have been replaced
by
rock
sediments. Can you can you find soft
tissue in there that survived 55 million
years? Is it possible to recover the
soft tissue which may contain perhaps
some DNA? For that you have to break all
the fossils and and look within the bone
cavities you know within the bones you
have bone marrow etc and so on. So you
would have to first of all go and break
all the fossils and see if there's any
soft tissue left which is almost an
impossibility but not quite impossible
because I do remember reading this 10 15
years ago that somebody was transporting
a Tyrannosaurus Rex sample a femur thigh
bone and somehow the workers messed up
and the the the
the specimen which was being transported
by crane it fell the thigh bone broke
and inside they found soft tissue wet
tissue
And when the tissue was examined, they
found things that look like blood
cells. T-Rex lived a 100 I don't know
how many years ago. Tyrannosaurus Rex.
How old is it? T-Rex. Uh, how
old? Uh, when did T-Rex live? Okay.
Yeah, it died. It died out 66 million
years ago with the extinction of the
non-avian
dinosaurs. So, it's possible. But the
probability the probability is extremely
low. Uh but if they do discover let's
say uh cambeium DNA then they could try
and do something with that. Is there
could there be adverse effects? Well,
not really as such. Uh the animal that
you bring back let's say you bring back
the woolly mammoth. I mean where will it
live? That's the question. It will be
adverse for the new new new specimens
that you are generating because it will
not have the environment. It it
it evolved to live in the woolly mammoth
went extinct about 10,000 or so years
ago because of the end of the ice age
and because of human hunting. It was it
was an animal that could only thrive in
extreme cold. Today we don't have it.
Where will it live and so on? Uh the
adverse effects will happen if you
revive ancient viruses or bacteria.
That's what we don't want.
So Priam Shirinasan says, "What are your
thoughts on Hotmail co-founder Samir
Bhya's recent statement regarding Indian
engineers?" He said that 99% of Indian
engineers lack hands-on skills and
mainly aspire for managerial positions.
Do you think he is giving unnecessary
yan or a reality check? He's absolutely
correct. And this is not meant to be a
criticism of the engineers. This is
meant to be a criticism of a criticism
of India's rotten education system. You
understand? Most Indian engineers, how
do you get a degree? You get a degree by
memorizing and mugging up texts and
writing exams. You all you learn is how
to pass exams and clear exams with high
marks. That's all you learn. You don't
really learn the skills needed to be an
engineer. Engineering skills are
hands-on skills. You have to do things.
You have to make, break, and modify
things. That's engineering. But in
engineering degrees today, what do you
learn? Memory. Memorize. Memorize.
Memorize. Pass exams. Pass exams. Some
field work, some lab work. But it's it
doesn't really give you the skills. The
only way you get skills is by doing
things over and over and over again.
That's the only thing you do. That's the
only way you learn skills. The education
system is garbage. It's rotten in India.
And Sabir Bya obviously is naturally
frustrated because he's an Indian. And
what he sees engineers coming from India
who don't know what they're doing,
right?
So it's not a criticism of the
individuals, it's a criticism of the
system. And he's absolutely 100%
correct. It's a criticism of the
education system. The corrupt rotten
education system that doesn't give India
what India would expect from an
education
system. Uh I have spoken at length about
education in episode between 28 and 33
somewhere around that time, three
episodes. So you can check it out over
there. But I completely agree with
Sabiata and in instead of getting angry
angry with him try and understand what
he is saying. That's what what I would
say to most people. Some people have
become upset. Some people are angry that
he said such things. He is absolutely
right. Okay. Caphile says
um why did Sauté always make films that
glamorized poverty? Was it to cater to
with the western audience as they always
liked seeing films that depicted India
as a disastrously poor nation like Slum
Dog Millionaire and so
on? I have no idea what old boy is so I
haven't seen
it. Um
Satyajitra I never liked watching Satyad
movies extremely depressing movies. I
know this is going to be a very
controversial thing to say and I'll get
a lot of hate especially from some parts
of India fine I don't I don't care all
as a kid sometimes you know on dur dan
they used to play those sachad movies
what pair panchali and whatn not
abject misery was what was showed in the
movies I'm sure there must be some good
angle about the human condition and
something but the movies showed India as
a nation of abject poverty and complete
brutal misery. That's all it showed. I
could not stand watching those movies.
Opur Shan Shar Pair Panchchali. I don't
know what these things mean. I don't
want to know. I couldn't I just couldn't
I I am not that kind of person. I don't
like misery. I don't like sadness. Yeah,
there is misery and sadness in the
world. But as an artist, you want to
make the world a better place. Okay.
Sure. Uh you can also represent the
country. I mean represent what's what's
happening in the world. But I saw that
he only focused on these
things. As an artist, you should have a
360°ree perspective. Okay, there's bad
stuff in the world. Let's draw the
world's attention to that. Sure. Okay,
this is this bad stuff happening and
people are somehow surviving. But you
also show some optimism, some
positivity, something nice. Create
something of
beauty. There are people in this country
in India who think that there is beauty
in misery. There is beauty in decay.
There is beauty in
decrepitude. He was one of those people.
And the fact is that if he had shown
India as a wonderful country, if he had
shown the beauty of India, which India
is is full of, then he would have never
got that Oscar in on his deathbed,
right? He was given a nice little pat on
the head when he was dying. When they
gave him an Oscar and some lady wearing
a sari announced it.
I am no fan of Satra. Let this be
controversial. Let me get hate. I don't
care. Facts are facts. Guy was obsessed
with misery and poverty. I don't care
how good or or director he may or may
not have been. I just don't care. Didn't
like his work.
Ro Rhodit Tarkar says why don't we get
any portraits hand handdrawn pictures or
any statues of our ancient Indian kings
like many ancient Chinese and European
kings our magnificent temples leave no
room for doubt that ancient India had
some super talented artists and
engineers no question about it why don't
we get this because everything was
destroyed
because when the Turks took over they
sought to destroy everything that was
made in the image of man they were their
religion is against the against uh
depiction of living being depictions of
human beings I think whatever so they
want to destroy all mortis all statues
all idols and especially when you want
to destroy a nation and its culture you
cannot allow statues of great kings
paintings of great kings queens
goddesses whoever to gods goddesses to
remain you destroy it all to show how
much stronger you are than the people
who you are subjugating. See, I have
destroyed all your statues. What will
you do about it? That's a thing. So, we
don't have any of it. Everything is
gone.
Um, one of the most common things is
India is full of statues of the Buddha.
And if you look at statues of Buddha,
most of them are headless. So, for
example, Buddha
statue statue
uh let's go for
Afghanistan.
Ah,
Afghanistan. I mean, we know what they
did to the Taliban to to the Bameyian
Buddhas. Look at all these statues.
Beautiful statues from Mass Inac etc.
Oh, this one has a
head. But yeah, you find so many
headless statues of Buddha. Let's look
at
Kaneshka. Ganeshka
statue. Okay. What do we find? We find
headless statues. I don't think this is
Kaneshka. Kaneshka did not look like
this because I know what he looked like
from his coins. Kaneshka was a big
bearded
guy and this is not a bearded guy. So
this is not Kesan. This is Kaneshka. You
see this? That's our man Kaneshka. So
this was a statue of Kaneshka. I think
they found it in Matura or somewhere.
They took his head off the
invaders and so on. This is a statue
from Gandhar. And you have a Taliban
like like person standing next to this.
So you can see that they're wearing
similar
dresses uh and so on. You see surotal
whatever. So the invaders uh
deliberately destroyed all the statues
and that's why we don't have it. And if
there were any paintings that would have
been destroyed or
burned. So the only statues of kings or
paintings of kings are from the last I
don't know 200 or so years that we have.
The ancient ones are all gone. Cuckoo
finished.
Um, geopolitical duba says, "Do you
think Nepal can become a monarchy again
in the near future?" Nepal was a
monarchy. It was the last Hindu nation
on the world and the monarchy was
destroyed by external
forces. Let's not discuss who what that
external force was. Let's not do that.
So, if Nepal is to become a monarchy
again in the near future or whenever, it
may only happen if an external force
makes this happen.
Um, I know that the people are sick and
tired of the of the allegedly corrupt
politicians or allegedly incompetent
politicians in Nepal. I'm sure the
public is sick and tired of that. And
I'm sure the public most the majority of
the public I I believe I get the sense
the majority of the population of Nepal
wants to the nation to revert to being a
monarchy. That's the sense I'm getting
from whatever I'm hearing and seeing.
Some may be opposed to it, but I don't
care. The majority is what matters in a
democracy, right?
But the people, politicians in power, do
you think they care about the majority?
What they want? They care about
remaining in power. And they won't allow
this to happen. Um, and they own the
means of violence. In Marxism, we have
the means of production. In political
theory, we have the means of violence.
The politicians control the means of
violence. So, the public can't do a
thing. Um, so I don't think monarchy
will return unless there is external
intervention. Now from where would an
external intervention for the
restoration of a Hindu monarchy come? I
wonder that's the
question.
Okay. Again says what says can you tell
us something about the Kir Rouge and the
Polep? Why did that person massacre so
many of his people? So this happened in
Cambodia. Let's go to the map because
we're discussing uh places. We go to
map. So let's put the map of the world
on the
screen and we are talking about
Cambodia.
Cambouesh. So let me show you where it
is. We know where India is. Let's go
eastwards. This time we go eastwards. We
cross the far east of India. We enter
Myanmar. We go south.
we go south of Thailand and here we have
this country wonderful country of
Cambodia which was destroyed by the Kir
Rouge. Okay. Uh so this is where it
happened first of all. Now let's go off
the map and and it was eventually I
think Paul took over in 1975 and Vietnam
liberated the country in 1979. Vietnam,
a communist nation, liberated Cambodia
from brutal rouge communist
terrorists. Okay, very very very strange
story.
So, you know, in the 1980s, I was a kid
in
Switzerland and uh as a boy, you often
go to the barber to have a
haircut. And in the 1980s in Europe,
they would have book they would have
magazines in the barber shop because you
have to wait for your turn. Somebody
else is getting a haircut, you have to
wait half an hour, maybe sometimes,
maybe 15 minutes. So there are magazines
kept over there for people to kill time
and those magazines are not for kids. I
assure you of that. Okay. I discovered
it once. So that day I went to the
barber shop and I had about 15 20
minutes to wait. So I picked up a
magazine and it was a news week or
something like that. It was about news.
Open the magazine and my goodness I see
these horrific images. It's the mid80s.
Okay. I see these extraordinarily
horrific images of some nation in
Asia and there are it's a rural nation
and on both sides of the little country
roads you have ditches that are dug and
they are filled with rotting human
bodies. As a kid you should not have to
see such things but people experienced
that people lived through this and I saw
these images and I was horrified and
then I read a bit and it's Cambodia and
I saw the term k rouge there and the
images discard me I was what like eight
I don't know I was a kid less than 10
years less than 10 years old for sure my
god those images are so so now let me
tell you what the and the person who did
that carnage just fields filled with
Dead bodies rotting under the
sun. Oh my god, those images still.
Okay, so the person who did this was
Pulpot. He was uh Cambodian. He studied
in France. In France, he became infected
with uh communist ideas, Marxist
ideas. He was studying in some uh
technical school, engineering or
something. He was studying some sort
some form of engineering and he got
exposure to communist ideas. He became a
communist. He comes back to Cambodia. Uh
he and the the nation of Cambodia was a
monarchy. It was run the king was um
Narotam Sihanuk. Normuk which is Narotam
Sihanuk. And he had been overthrown in a
coup. So Narotam Sihanuk was in exile.
So this guy Paul Pot starts a guerilla
insurgency and this fellow the king
Narotam Sihanuk joins hands with the Kir
Rouge which is the organization that
Paul Pot becomes the head of and they
try to take back power in Cambodia by
overthrowing the guy who did the coup
and then eventually there's this long
civil war and eventually uh the CL Rouge
this Mauist organization headed by Paul
Po it takes takes over the country. They
enter the capital city, Fnen. They order
everybody to evacuate the city. It's a
big city. It's a metropolitan city.
Maybe a million plus population perhaps.
I don't remember exactly. Big
city. They order everyone to evacuate
the city. Everybody is out of the city.
Everybody goes to the
fields. So there are people, there are
doctors doing surgeries, they are thrown
out. If you wear glasses, you are an
enemy of the state. If you are educated,
if you know how to read and write,
you're an enemy of the
state and um they they they displace the
entire population of all the cities and
towns and villages of the country. They
put them all in the fields of the
country. They give them manual labor to
do and then they start hunting down
people who are class enemies. Class
enemies. We discussed Marxism in the
beginning of the show, didn't we?
Oppressors versus oppressed. Anyone who
could read, who could write, anyone who
wore glasses, anybody who had a watch
was the enemy. And they would be
murdered in the most horrific ways. They
would be taken
to swall, what is the name of the prison
in Swampen? They call it the Hanoi
Hilton or something. No, that was
different. That was different. Um, TW
slang prison or something. I forget the
exact name. In which they would process
every person, take photographs, men,
women,
children. And look, I will not even
describe the brutalities of what they
did. Uh the nation had a population of
about 7 or so million at the time. From
79 to from 1975 to 79, the population
came down by according to various
reports between 1 million to 5 million
decrease of population which means they
killed between 1 to 5 million people in
just four
years through and the brutality was
incredible. Ah
uh that that's Paul Pot. Why did he
massacre people? Because he wanted to be
in power. He wanted to first come to
power then he wanted to retain power.
And he do that by brutalizing and
terrorizing the people. And he believed
in Marxism. He was an ardent believer in
Marxism Paul. So he implemented his
version of Marxism. He was a Mauist
essentially. Um so that's what communism
do. Since we are discussing this this
individual uh let me put
his it it makes sense to put a face to
to the name right so this is Paul
Pot this is what the person looks like
as you can there where is it here we
have it that was his face that's Paul
Poth
and this is a small sample of what he
ended up
doing. Okay. Uh Cambodia is okay. And
and the king was Narotam.
Narotam
Sihanuk. This guy who died in 2012 or
something. He's he his reputation is
forever tainted by his association with
the Kir Rouge and
Pulpot. and he had lots of children
uh including prince Narotamarid
uh who never became king and princess
Dvi who was a who was a dancer classical
dancer and so on. Anyhow I will not go
into the into the details but you get
the point. Paulpot is one of the great
monsters of human history who killed I
don't know how many of his own people.
Absolute
monster. Okay, let's take some more a
few more questions and then then I then
we'll do I'll take questions from the
live
chat. Vidy man says can you educate
about fasting? It's is it true that 96
hours of fasting creates good changes in
our body? If if yes, please explain.
Look, um this entire
um this entire thing that we have of
eating three meals a day, it's nonsense.
Okay? This this uh c this tradition of
eating three meals a day plus snacks
plus whatnot was created by by by the by
industrial by commercial pressures to
sell more fast food, more junk food and
all that. As as a species homo sapiens,
we have evolved with a fast or feast
approach to
life. And our bodies are not
accustomed to to be able to process
three meals a day, four meals a day.
Historically, we were hunter gatherers
for the longest period, hundreds of
thousands of years. It's just in the
past 10,000 years that we have become an
agricultural and sedentary species. It's
it's only in the past 70 years that we
have become, you know, even more
sedentary. That's a eyeblink of time in
the evolutionary time scale. So our
bodies aren't adapted for
that. Our bodies are adapted to eating
sparingly. Our body the our bodies are
are adapted they're designed to be
runners. We are designed to be runners,
not walkers, not sitters, runners. Our
ancestors ran all
day and our ancestors would eat like two
or three meals in a week perhaps at the
best of times. When you eat you feast
then you starve then you then you fast.
So fasting because of these because of
these reasons because of these
evolutionary reasons fasting is good for
health and uh you know research and
medical studies have shown that if you
fast for 4 days which is 96 hours uh it
you you it has the effect of completely
regenerating your immune
system. So all of your immune cells are
regenerated and you get a completely
brand new immune system if you fast for
96 hours 4 days. I think most people
would have a heart attack at the idea of
fasting for 4 days, not eating food for
4 days, it's nothing whatsoever. If you
are a healthy person with no actual
underlying health conditions, it's no
big deal to fast for 4 days. Just drink
water. You will have absolutely no ill
effects. You'll actually end up with a
new immune system. That's what medical
science has shown us. Now there is
something called extended
fasting which is fasting more than 4
days just water zero
calories. What that
does it does multiple things. First of
all the longer you fast the more
autophagy your body uh uh under goes
autophagy autophagy means once you start
fasting the body starts recycling
itself. At any given point in time in
your body, you'll have uh dying cells,
damaged cells, diseased cells, maybe
precancerous cells. Okay, these cells
are not good for your health. Now, if
you start fasting for an extended period
of time, 2 days, 3 days, 4 days or more,
then the body starts doing
housekeeping internally. So it starts
identifying the cells and destroying
them and then taking the components and
building new cells out of that. So if
you fast for let's say a week you will
undergo significant autophagy and a lot
of all these dead dying diseased
precancerous cells if any will be
destroyed. And if you fast even longer
the the better is going to be the
effect. It's going to detoxify your
whole body. It will clean your liver and
your kidneys and whatnot. um it will
throw your body into ketosis which is it
will burn ketones, it will burn fat
instead of of of of glycogen instead of
glucose for energy which gives you a
whole different u feeling and so on. So
yeah extended fasting is um not for
everybody I assure you of that but 3 4
days anybody can do it and
I am experienced with extended fasting.
I've done it a few times. My longest
fast was 23 days. Only water, zero
calories. And my second longest fast was
21 days. Again, zero calories, just
water. Um, so yeah, it can be done. It's
not easy. It's it's rather brutal, but
it has its health benefits. But I assure
you, it's not for
everybody. Okay, with that, let's take
some questions from the live chat. From
the live
chat, Shri Raandra Anama says, "What's
what are your views on Austria? I regard
it as a country that exists. I don't
have any specific views about it. It's
not geopolitically very significant.
It's part of the EU which means it is
part which means it is not a sovereign
nation and it has an interesting history
part of the AustroHungarian Empire.
Vienna is the capital and so on. And of
course um there is an interesting person
who associated with Austria. Some would
call him the painter. So yeah, that's
what I'll
say. Okay, some more questions. Come on.
Come on. Come on. Come on. Um, Pratam
says, "When will we see an Indian UFC
champ? How many years?" I'm sure there's
somebody out there. If you train him or
her well now, they could become a UFC
champ. Um, what we should look, we
should have all sports in India. UFC is
a brutal sport. It's a it's sport of
fighting. It's not for everybody. But
there are people who need that. There
are people who with the violent that
that violent streak in them that needs
to be tamed and disciplined. And you can
only do it by putting them in the in the
fighting arena so that they can channel
that in the right direction and such
people will bring India great glory in
in the sporting field. So if we make
these this this sport widespread in
India, we'll have the UFC champ
tomorrow. It all depends on the
resources we give to the people. But
there's no question that we have all the
genetics, all the stuff we need to
become
champions. All right.
um moving charge with a magnetic field
says how much information does the
Indian government hide from its
citizens? Well, if I knew then I would
be part of the Indian government but I'm
not so I don't know but it makes sense
for any government to hide some things
from the public for national security
reasons or whatever reasons. So I'm
going to I'm pretty sure there are some
things that are kept secret that are
classified as top secret above top
secret whatever else class various
classifications every nation has these
things and it's there for a reason. Uh
how much is there I'm not sure but yeah
there is going to be a wheel of secrecy
over certain things and it needs to be
there. Okay.
Aayush Singh says, "Is China lying about
its 5% economic growth as its prop as
its property sector which is 30% of GDP
has collapsed?" Well,
look, am I the right person to ask this?
Because I can only give you the right
answer if I have the actual data, facts,
statistics, and figures in front of me.
But I don't, right? I'm not in the
Chinese government. I'm not at the level
of Xiinping who knows everything that's
happening in China. So, I can only guess
and then I can only speculate. So I
don't know. That's the answer. Look, I
don't know. If if somebody claims they
know what's happening, they're lying to
you. Please understand
this. This data, these facts and figures
are only available at the highest
echelons of the Chinese government,
Chinese Communist Party. Some people
claim that the property sector has
collapsed and whatnot. How do you know
that?
There are issues with the property
sector. Um because of societal social
reasons more than anything else. See
it's very property is quite cheap in
China. Everybody has one child. Okay?
Everybody has one child. Property is
super cheap. So everybody buys let's say
a
flat. Everybody buys a
flat. So you have one child. Let's say
you have a boy and you have bought a
flat. Now you say that I have extra
money and my boy is getting is growing
up. So when he gets married I want him
to have his own flat. So you buy another
flat. So now you have two flats. Now
let's say there's another family who
have a daughter. They they also have
good money, decent money. They have a
flat. The girl is growing up. They think
okay let's buy a flat for her so that
when she gets married she will have a
flat. Now she has a flat. The boy has a
flat. They get married. There's an extra
flat somewhere right?
So there's so many flats like this that
are lying
empty. It's because property is cheap in
China and people can afford things. The
purchasing power of of the Chinese uh
yuan is quite a bit. Food is super cheap
in China. Lots of stuff is super cheap.
So we have to look at it from a Chinese
lens, not from a from an outsers's lens
if you want to do justice to your
analysis, if you want to be fair in your
assessment.
So I think there are nuances in
everything. I think uh there is a
tendency especially in the west to
demonize China. There is also a tendency
in India to look at China from a
perspect perspective of suspicion and
enmity. And for that the Chinese are
responsible.
Okay. But if you really want to
understand the world you have to look at
it from a proper perspective. And I
think it's more than what it's made out
to
be. Mr. 88 says, "Have you watched any
Gibli movies? I'm sure you would like
them even though they're animation
movies." I haven't watched any Gibli
movies. Uh, is is The Grave of the
Fireflies a Giblly movie? I was about to
watch it, but I didn't find the time. I
hear it's a very sad, tragic story, but
a very highly rated movie. So, I haven't
seen them. I've seen still images, Gibli
art, beautiful art. Um, you know, I I am
not opposed to animation movies. As a
kid, I as a kid that's all I wanted to
watch,
cartoons. I still don't mind watching
good animation. So, yeah,
absolutely. Um, all right.
Okay. Um, let's
uh let's see some more questions if I
can find something interesting.
Um um
um my views on this person, my views on
that person. I have no views on people
that don't matter. For me, the kind of
people that matter are at the prime
minister level, the Elon Musk level, the
Julius Caesar and Shingish Khan level. I
will not comment about some comedian. I
will not comment about some YouTuber. I
am a YouTuber. Yeah. So that's why I
believe I am not worthy of being
commented about. I'm not that important.
So please understand you have to really
matter in the world only then people
should discuss you
uh okay let's
um okay Kalpana says what does Kalpana
say I have a theory that the El Dorado
city of gold must be our own Lanka after
all it was also a city of gold in
Atlantis could be dwara what can you
comment about this El Dorado is this
reputed city made of gold in the
Americas, El
Dorado, city of gold. Now, Kalpana has
the theory that this must be our own
Lanka because Lanka was called Suni
Lanka, city of gold. Atlantis could be
dara. What's my thing of belief? What's
my comment on this? Um I don't know
about Atlantis Darka that that rel that
hypothetical relationship. See, um,
Atlantis, this the story of Atlantis
came from what? Plateau, Aristotle, one
of these guys. And, uh, that's Greece.
So, that's about 3,000 years ago, let's
say, roughly. Yeah. 3,000, maybe 2 and a
half thousand. But let's give it 3,000
years just to make it a round number.
So, maybe these fellows, they heard the
story 3,000 years ago. Now, Dwara is
definitely older than 3,000 years. So it
could be that they heard the story of
this great city that went under the
ocean because of the earthquake and then
they the the Greeks called it Atlantis
but the story came from India. It's
possible. Yeah. So I think there is a
small possibility. I will not say it's
guaranteed that this is the one. Yes.
Atlantis is dar I won't say that. I'm
saying it's
possible. We cannot discount the
possibility. Maybe the possibility is
slightly small but it is a possibility.
And I am open to considering it. That's
what I'll say. Um, El Dorado and Sri
Lanka. Now, Sri Lanka was called a city
of gold back in the day. I don't know
how many thousands of years ago during
the Ramayan era. The El Dorado that the
Spaniards were looking for was a
different city. I promise you of that.
Let me tell you the story. Do we have
time? The Spaniards were driven by this
greed, this lust for
gold. Okay. So their their guy
Christopher Don Christobal Colon
Christopher Columbus had had discovered
this new world and he had come back to
Spain with promises that there is gold
out there so that he could have a great
career as a conqueror as as a governor
of Espanola and so on. It didn't end
well for him but the the stories
inflamed the whole of Spain that there's
gold out there plenty of gold and then
they were able to find some gold. They
disco they destroyed the Inca Empire.
Franchesco Pidaro was it was Heran
Cortez. It was
Pizaro of gold. So they thought there is
a city out there somewhere in the
jungles which has so much gold all the
other gold in the world becomes obsolete
and there were stories of Sibola the
seven cities of gold which came from uh
during the uh before the Spanish
reconista and so on. because of all
these myths and legends and so on also
because of uh stories associated with uh
what's his
name I forget the name right now lots of
names so because of these stories you
know you had uh this myth that was
created of El Dorado a city of gold it
has nothing to do with Lanka it was a
myth in the Spanish imag
imagination they were looking for that
not for Lanka that I can tell
Rik says how to achieve redness in life
up first of all understand yourself most
people don't spend the time to
understand themselves they don't take
the time to understand themselves to
understand yourself you would be alone
people are scared to be alone you first
have to understand yourself which means
you understand your strengths and
weaknesses then you you build on the
strengths by raising your standards and
working as hard as possible you don't
achieve greatness by being a part-time
worker or whatever. You have to work you
work really hard and some people
discover it very late. It is what it is.
Yeah.
So, it's it's a process. It's a long
process. All right. With that, I'm going
to end today's session. Once again, 2
hours 17 minutes almost. So, thank you
so much. Apologies to those of you whose
questions are still there. I'm sorry I
can't take all the questions in one
session, but please keep ask. Okay. How
about next weekend we do a question only
based on the live chat so that you all
get the chance to ask questions. Okay,
next weekend, next Saturday, I'll take
questions only from the live chat. No
questions from the comments. All right,
thank you so much. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
Keep working hard and take care of
yourselves. And I'll see you next
weekend. Thank you.